<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://tyrex.exolab.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Tyrex</title>

    <header>
      <p>Tyrex is the missing piece in the J2EE puzzle, a J2EE service provider for both
         Servlet and EJB container, JMS providers and generic connectors. It provides
         services for security and authentication, local and distributed transactions,
         resource configuration and pooling, and TP monitoring. Tyrex is presently
         integrated with Tomcat and OpenEJB.</p>

      <p><b>Note:</b> Presently we are only hosting one mailing list. Traffic is not high, so if
         you are interested in keeping up to date with new releases, please <a href="lists.xml">subscribe
         to this list</a>.</p>

    </header>

    <section title="Features">

      <p>Short feature list (we haven't got all day):
        <ul>
          <li>Full support for JTA and OTS transactions APIs</li>
          <li>Support for local and distributed transactions</li>
          <li>JAAS-based authentication, LDAP login module</li>
          <li>Configurable transaction processing monitor</li>
          <li>JDBC pooling and automatic JDBC resource enlistment</li>
          <li>Connector architecture</li>
          <li>XML/JNDI based configuration</li>
          <li>JNDI environment naming context</li>
          <li>Transaction context propagation over IIOP and RMI</li>
          <li>Tomcat 3.1 connector</li>
        </ul></p>

    </section>

    <section title="News">
      <p>Version $VERSION$ is now <a href="download.xml">available for download</a>.
      <ul>
        <li>April 10, 2000: Version 0.9.5</li>
        <li>Feb 10, 2000: Version 0.9.4</li>
        <li>Dec 21, 1999: Version 0.9</li>
      </ul>
       See the <a href="changelog.xml">change log page</a> for more information.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="About Tyrex">

      <p>Tyrex is the missing piece in the J2EE puzzle, the hidden back end behind the
         Servlet, EJB and JMS servers. Tyrex was originally developed as a separate back-end
         that can be used with Tomcat, OpenEJB, OpenJMS and a variety of other servers.
         Due to its nature as a back-end system, Tyrex is probably one of the most boring
         open source projects on earth.</p>

      <p>Most of the code released in Tyrex has been developed by Assaf Arkin, CTO
         &lt;<email>arkin@exoffice.com</email>&gt;. Contributors are welcome
         to join this project. Please join us on the <a href="lists.xml">mailing
list</a>.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
